<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Lively pourtraicture of the face of this common-wealth exactly drawn by Lewis the Fourth of France of famous memory.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2594A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30995</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11760226</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11760226</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48667</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48757)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1486:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Lively pourtraicture of the face of this common-wealth exactly drawn by Lewis the Fourth of France of famous memory.</title>
                  <author>Louis IV, King of France, 921-954.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Engraved t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48667:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48667:1"/>
            <p>A Lively POURTRAICTURE OF THE FACE OF THIS COMMON-WEALTH, Exactly drawn <hi>By LEWIS the Fourth,</hi> OF FRANCE, Of Famous Memory.</p>
            <p>Printed in the year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48667:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48667:2"/>
            <head>LEWIS THE FOURTH, To his Revolted Subjects.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I ſhall receive your Oath of Fidelity, which I may juſtly demand, and you ought dutifully to take, I ſhall let you know you have recalled (this day) a Prince (who du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Exile) had nothing elſe to do, but to ſtudy how to Rule and Reign; and hereby I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force you to believe that you ſhall not be able to make a Royal Throne a paſſage into my Fathers priſon: And after you have preſented me with a Crown, to dare to wiſh me ſo much ill, as once to think of Chains &amp; Irons. I know well, that this diſcourſe will ſurpriſe you, and that you did not believe when you preſented me with a Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that I ſhould not rather have received it with Thanks, then Reprehenſions; but this act is extraordinary in its commencement, in its progreſs, and in its concluſion; and it is juſt that all circumſtances ſhould be proportionable. Let it then ſuffice you onely to know, that if I be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to what point Subjects are to pay their obeiſance, yet I am not ignorant to what degree Soveraigns may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their clemency: Notwithſtanding there is this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt them, that the <hi>Subjects have no limits for the firſt, but Soveraigns have for the latter. The People are obliged to the Princes wills, both by their Births and their Lawes. They owe them their goods, their lives and their liberties; and their Princes owe them nothing but Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48667:3"/>which can hardly pardon Traytors.</hi> If theſe Truths and Maximes had been equally underſtood, and followed by the late King my Soveraign, and you his People, affairs had not been in that ſad condition as they now are. The State had not been reduc'd to ſuch confuſion; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces had not been Cantonized; <hi>Germany</hi> had not been ſo full of Factions; <hi>Italy</hi> had not been ſo divided; all the Cities of the kingdom had not had ſo many kings as they now have Governours; you had not been guilty of the crime of Treaſon, in elevating an Uſurper to the Throne, the King my Father might ſtill have Reigned, or (at leaſt) I might have received the Crown from his hands, and not from yours; his Tomb might have been bedewed with my tears, his Scepter had not been prophaned, his Hearſe might have been covered with Trophies, and not with Chains. And (to ſpeak all in a few words) you might have been <hi>happy and innocent.</hi> But as his <hi>Clemency,</hi> and your <hi>Rebellion</hi> were the ſole cauſers of all theſe evils, ſo your <hi>Obedience,</hi> and my <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> are the onely means to make reparation. Conſider a little (I pray you) (that you fall not back in the ſame eſtate wherein you were) in what Relation you now ſtand; and in what condition I am. Firſt, you have violated all ſorts of Rights in the perſon of your King, you have raiſed a War againſt him; you have aſſaulted him, and afterwards poyſoned him; you have abuſed the confidence he had in you, you have detained him priſoner with as great <hi>Treaſon</hi> as <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> with as great <hi>inſolency</hi> as <hi>cruelty:</hi> an <hi>injury</hi> which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offered (hardly) to the perſon of an ordinary <hi>Herald.</hi> Thus you have violated, and impudently abuſed your <hi>King;</hi> you have detained him priſoner during a Treatie of Peace, for five years together led him from priſon to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48667:3"/>priſon; you have forced him not only to ſet by his <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> and to depoſe his Crown; but you have conſtrain'd him with violence to transferre it into other hands then mine. To conclude, you put him to death, and you have reduced my ſelf to a ſtrict neceſſitie, to ſearch my ſafetie in my flight, and to go and ſhew my miſerie beyond the Seas. Yet this is not all, you have done one thing which never any did before, it hath been ſeen ſometimes that the <hi>Grandees</hi> of a Kingdom have interpoſed themſelves againſt a <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and have deſtroied it; but 'twas never ſeen that they themſelves elevated a <hi>Tyrant</hi> to the Throne as <hi>you</hi> have done: In theſe kind of crimes the Abettors may be ſaid to be more criminal then he who hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all the fruit: For if each one of you in particular had aſpired to ſet the Crown upon his own head, you might have been more excuſable, then to have ſnatcht it from your lawfull <hi>Prince</hi> to place it on the head of an <hi>Vſurper.</hi> But you'l ſay to me, <hi>the Prince that bore it was not able to ſupport it.</hi> To that I ſhall anſwer, As I have the honour to be his Son, and was his Subject, it belongeth not to me to determine what he <hi>could,</hi> or what he <hi>could not:</hi> ſeeing he was my <hi>Father,</hi> I ought not to preſume to be his judge, and ſeeing he was my King, I ought not to be ſo impudent to cenſure, much leſſe to condemne his actions, he being not obliged to render an account to any, <hi>But God alone.</hi> Believe then, the ſame reſpect I have for his memorie, you ought to have had for his perſon, he was your King as well as mine: ſeeing then that <hi>Kings are called the Fathers of the people,</hi> Their Subjects are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to have for them a true reſentment of a reſpect, which their very birth may infuſe into them: Beſides, as <hi>Soveraigns are the true Images of God, and that the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48667:4"/>of their puiſſance is a beam and ray of his power;</hi> Subjects ought to have an equall ſubmiſſion to their Soveraigns will. When you ſee a Comet appear, the Sun eclipſed, the Thunder bolt fall on innocent heads, when you ſee Floods drown whole Towns, by their inundation, and the Sea (paſſing his bounds, and ſwallowing whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces in the bottome of the deep) devour them up: When you ſee an Earthquake make Kingdoms tremble, and cauſe horrid devaſtations of whole Countries, then (I ſay) it is permitted to the People to murmure? Do you not diſcern the contrarie, how in theſe occurrences they redouble their vowes and prayers, and that they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more obedient to God, then at ſuch a time, as if God had forſaken his providence of the Vniverſe? and when it shall ſo happen, that Heaven (for the punishment of your ſins) gives you a Prince under whoſe Reign <hi>policy</hi> and <hi>prudence</hi> are not well obſerved, during whoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment Forraign and Civill Wars devour all with cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell ravages: it belongeth not then to you to reprehend and condemn your Soveraign; for, is he feeble? then you ought to ſuſtain him: is he unfortunate? you ought to bemoan him: is he wicked? you ought to look upon him as a ſcourge and chaſtiſement ſent from Heaven, and to wait with Patience for a remedie from that hand, which hath cauſed your evil. For when a Prince commands an Armie, and gives Battail; if it ſo happen that the Souldiers perform not their devoires and dutie, that his ſquadrons yield, the main body be broken, and (in the end after he hath done even miracles in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he be yet conſtrained to quit the field, and to retreat from his Enemies? is it not the Prince that loſeth the Battail? Is it not the Prince that ſuffers the diſgrace? Is it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48667:4"/>not the Prince that is reputed vanquiſht? And that bears the loſs and infamie of the day? Notwithſtanding, that by his own particular actions he hath merited to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror? ſeeing it is thus, why will not you (in ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions) bear with the infirmities, and misfortunes of your Princes, as well as they do with yours? Or (to ſpeak ſomething yet nearer to the quick) why do you not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair theſe diſorders by your own more exact obedience? The Prince alone is obvious in a Battail to the infamie, Cowardiſe and misfortune of his whole Army, and you are thouſands, who are obliged to ſtrengthen the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and Honour of your King, which he cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port with his ſingle valour. Believe me, <hi>if all Subjects would be loyal, no Kingdome could be miſerable:</hi> and <hi>if all Princes thought more of ſeverity then of Clemencie, there would not be ſo many Subjects, Rebells.</hi> Moreover, if it were permitted to the Capritious people to take and give Crowns, when they fancied a change: I conceive there is not a Shepheard but might hope to be a King, and not a King but might be reduced to be a Shepherd; ſo unruly and uncertain are their floating judgements. But (to ſpeak the truth to you) theſe things ought not thus to paſs: we are your <hi>Maſters,</hi> and you ought not to become <hi>ours.</hi> It is not that I am ignorant that <hi>God diſpoſeth of Scepters and Crowns, as he pleaſes, &amp; gives them as he liſts, and beſtowes them on, or takes them from whom he will, and what he alwaies doth is without all injuſtice; ſometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that the people ſhalelevate to the Throne, thoſe who never pretended to ſuch a high degree. But when ſuch an accident happeneth, it is uſually in favour to thoſe extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary perſons in whom Virtue hath impreſt a Royal Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter ſo viſible, that it were almost injuſtice not to admit
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48667:5"/>them Kings.</hi> To conclude, that which precedes, and that which followes, ought to be ſufficient to juſtifie the effect, and it became <hi>Charles Martel, Pepin,</hi> and <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemain</hi> puiſſantly to erect a Throne, which was not foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon a line of right ſucceſſion, yet even in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encounter you will ſee the event to this preſent hath not authorized your deſign; The Engine of this enterprize hath been ſlain in battail: The <hi>Arch biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rhemes</hi> preſerved not his life, but three daies after he had anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the uſurper. But it is not ſeaſonable (to day) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerate the injuſtice of your proceedings; I am not willing to particularize other things, and I ſhall ſatisfie my ſelf with telling you, in generall, that <hi>Kings ought not to loſe their Crowns, but with their lives, and that nothing can diſpenſe Subjects from the reſpect, and loyaltie, which they owe to their Soveraignes, nor any pretence (whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) Authorize Treaſon and Rebellion. If ſacred perſons</hi> may not enjoy their particular priviledge, <hi>(which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from none but God)</hi> they ſhall be expoſed, more then others, to all ſorts of miſeries; Their guards will appear to them inſtead of enemies, their Thrones will rather ſeem a direfull precipice then a place of honour, and ſafetie; a <hi>King (of this kind)</hi> is no better then an <hi>illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious ſlave,</hi> when he ſhall have as many Maſters as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. This firſt diſorder will quickly cauſe a ſecond, for when the <hi>Nobles</hi> of a Kingdom fail in their dutie to their <hi>Prince,</hi> their own <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> and <hi>Tenants</hi> will forfeit their fealtie to them, and then <hi>Rebellion</hi> communicated from the <hi>Grandees</hi> to the <hi>Commons,</hi> and ſo deſcending from one Soul to another, an univerſall confuſion ſwells and devours all. <hi>Every one will command, and no perſon obey,</hi> (and in this reſentment of <hi>Levelling equality</hi>) <hi>each perſon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48667:5"/>proves a ſlave to his own ambition, and no one, either rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally Commands himſelf or others.</hi> In effect, this is the moſt ſad condition that a Kingdom can fall into, when there is no ſubjection, and where (for their puniſhment) the Prince hath not force to reduce the people to their obedience. For mine own part, when I conſider my ſelf to be the Son of a King, the ſucceſſour of ſo many Kings, and yet, notwithſtanding that I immediately ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not my Father: This <hi>Idea</hi> imprints in me, a ſtrange confuſion as towards you, and an extream grief as to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my ſelf: for when I reflect how the ſame Subjects who inchained <hi>Charles in Fetters,</hi> and gave the Crown to <hi>Robert,</hi> placed <hi>Lewis</hi> on the Throne, the malice which they bore to the Father, may it not eaſily fall upon the Son? and may not they fear that the Son will revenge the outrages committed againſt the Father? but yet (may ſome one ſay,) thoſe who have ſearcht after you, &amp; paſs'd the Seas to preſent you with a Scepter, they need not fear that the memorie of their ancient injuſtice will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liege you to puniſh them: They have reaſon rather to believe, that this ſubmiſſion ſhould blot out the memory of the firſt disſervice: It is certain, <hi>in the exact Rule of juſtice, no noble Action ought to paſſe without his recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence:</hi> and it is really as true, <hi>That no crime ought to eſcape without his puniſhment.</hi> After all theſe reaſons, what ought you not to fear? and what not to hope? you have recalled me to the Throne, 'tis true, but if you had not, had you not been as Criminall againſt <hi>Lewis,</hi> as you had been againſt <hi>Charles?</hi> he who gives to another, that which he hath taken from him, reſtores without doubt that which he hath taken, but his reſtoration is not a free preſent, and he ought not to expect thanks for an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48667:6"/>Action of that nature. No, it ſufficeth if one puniſh not the firſt, without intending any recompence for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. I may ſay alſo, that you underſtand not rightly all my preſent concernments; for why? becauſe you have not left me ſtill in exile, becauſe you have rendred what juſtly appertained to me, Becauſe you underſtood that I came to re-demand mine own, not with a powerfull Army: and (being tired with your crimes and miſeries) you believe you may probably diſarm the furie of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by this Act of juſtice: No, no, confide not in any of theſe pretenſes, for if I had not ſtronger conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then theſe, I ſhould commence my Reign with the puniſhment of your treaſons, I ſhould ſend them to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who reſtrained the perſon of my Father, and expoſe them to the moſt cruell tortures, who contrived and cauſed his death, with the greatneſſe of his misfortunes. Thoſe black crimes are ſuch which nothing can exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate; <hi>Repentance and tears for common errours, where humane frailty may plead excuſe, and not for Traitors and Rebels, nor for thoſe, who have deſtroied Thrones and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, inchaind Kings, created and protected Tyrants.</hi> Think not then, that by taking an Oath of fidelitie (which is your dutie) that I am thereby ingaged not to doe what becomes a King. No, I ſcorn a Throne where I ſhould be a ſlave, and I had rather be obſcured in priſon, as my Father was, then not to Reign as Soveraign. <hi>Thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with whom Loyalty is elective, forbear not to make their Kings abſolute, becauſe they could have no pretence of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to do otherwiſe:</hi> judge then, if thoſe who hold their Crowns from Heaven ought to acknowledge their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for their Maſters, and whether they ought not rather to puniſh, or pardon, as beſt agreeth with their pleaſure.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48667:6"/>In a word, <hi>I find it far more glorious to be a loyall Subject, then to be a King disobeyed.</hi> Prepare then your ſelves to render me all that obedience which you owe me, and (without farther informing you whether you are to hope more for Clemencie or Iuſtice) reſolve your ſelves to an abſolute ſubmiſſion, I know well ſome peeviſh Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litians will cenſure, that I act not as I ought in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, and that I ſhould reflect on former paſſages with ſome ſweetneſs, and gratifie you with Preſents, to encourage you with future hopes, but I preſume my Policy is more generous, and more ſecure then theirs; for if I had ſo perſwaded you, perhaps you would have believed me to have been more fit to wear my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Irons</hi> then his <hi>Crown;</hi> and would have more ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted me of weakneſs and diſſimulation, this exceſſive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence would give you more of fear, and me leſs of honour and eſtimation: I (being then ſo far from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Maximes) tell you once more, that I declare my ſelf to be your King. And (without farther capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation with you) I aſcend the Throne by the ſteps of mine own Authoritie as Soveraignly, as if not recalled by you at all. Hitherto I have let you know I am not ignorant how far the dutie of Subjects ought to bend: But moreover, I judge it fit to acquaint you to what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree Soveraign Clemencie may extend it ſelf; to this end, that by that reſentment, you may reaſonably know what to fear, and what to hope. Know then, that <hi>although a Prince may justly puniſh Traitors, he may likewiſe pardon penitent offenders, principally then, when he diſcerns his pardon ſhall reclaim inſolency to obedience, and fidelity:</hi> For, ſeeing Kings are the Fathers of the people, they ought not alwaies to be too ſevere in juſtice; and <hi>ſeeing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48667:7"/>that a Prince may afford grace and pardon to his enemies, he may without doubt ſhew pity and mercy to his own Subjects:</hi> He cannot well puniſh them all, but muſt (in part) enfee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf; nor ſluce out their blood without emptying his own veins; wherefore he ought to ſpare them as far as Reaſon and Iuſtice can make the way paſſable. When then a particular accident grows up againſt a Prince, or State, it may ſuffice that the heads of ſome chief offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors be ſacrificed to a reparation, and that by ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere examples others may be inſtructed with exemplarie terrour. But ſeeing that the number of the offendors may prove infinite, and if all ſhould be puniſh't, a deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of entire Provinces might ſucceed, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently more men be loſt then 15 main Battails could devour, ſo that the piles of dead corps ſhould make mountains, and ſevere execution of revenge cauſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of bloud: in ſuch conſiderations (I ſay) it may be better to uſe a greater example of Clemencie, then of Iuſtice, and hazard ſomething, rather then to looſe the lives of ſo many miſerable ſouls: and <hi>there cannot be a greater Victory then to vanquiſh ones own paſſion</hi> in ſuch dangerous conjunctures. Fear not then that I ſhall abuſe my Authoritie, ſince if I ſhould puniſh all who have offended, I ſhould reduce my Kingdom to a forlorn De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart: For who is there among you that hath not failed of his dutie? Some have done miſchief, others have deſired it, or at leaſt permitted it to be acted: ſome have aſſiſted <hi>Robert,</hi> others have directly fought againſt their King: ſome have moſt perfidiouſly laid their hands upon their <hi>Anointed Lord,</hi> &amp; committed a <hi>ſacred perſon</hi> into priſon, and others have (at leaſt forſaken him. <hi>The publick good is pretext of all things, but Rebellion alone is the mother of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48667:7"/>that horrid Monſter.</hi> The Nobles agitated (as they did) for their own intereſt, and the people by their madneſs, and unadviſedneſs, ſeconded their furie, and put in execution the intention of the Parricides: Your wives and your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are not exempt from theſe crimes, ſeeing (without doubt) they made vowes for their Parents offending, and praiers againſt their Prince. Whereas then I cannot pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you all, but that I muſt utterly exterminate you; it reſteth at my choice, whether I would become a King without Subjects, or to pardon you out of pure grace and bountie, and not by Obligations. It may be that during your lives you may repent you of your ancient crimes, and become as faithful as you have been diſobedient. But (perhaps you will tell me) as to our ſelves, we have repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted formerly before we ſent to you to come, and receive the Scepter which belongs to you. 'Tis true, it may be as you have ſaid, and that I have conſidered your Addreſſes to me were to make reparation of what formerly paſſed, and that with thoſe hands you would advance to the Throne his Son whoſe Father you had barbarouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. But (after all) <hi>whoſoever can abandon the path of Virtue to make choice of that Vice, can again embrace that occaſion if preſented.</hi> Wherefore you owe greater obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to me then I can conſidence to you; for had I not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſhew Grace and Pardon, the great number of Nobles which the King of <hi>England,</hi> my Uncle, hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me to attend my perſon, had not come without Souldiers; each one of theſe who incircle me have troops at their command: and I would not have received my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Crown but in the head of a victorious Armie, in the midſt of a Field covered with dead, and dying men; bedewed with the blood of ten thouſand Rebels: I would
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48667:8"/>have been the Conqueror of my Kingdom, and not have mounted unto the Throne ſupported by the ſame hands who ſnatcht it from my Fathers head. But I call to mind I am your King, as you are alſo my Subjects, and in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation I can love you yet, as guiltie as you are: I can have pittie for your errors, and kindneſs for your obſtinacie; and I will not put my ſelf into a condition of ſadneſs after the Victorie: I am then come to you without an Armie, to receive what is mine. This Action (without doubt) is hardie, bold, and well deſerveth glorie; and is ſufficiently obliging to demerit your acknowledgement in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of fidelitie. Before that you were criminous, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and humane right conjured you not to forſake your Prince; but this day a new obligation chaineth you to more ſtrict obedience. It is not enough alone to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo to ſatisfie your dutie; but it is your part to blot out the memorie of what is paſt, and to juſtifie what is preſent; you ought not to look on me meerly as your King, but as a King of your own choice, as a King who hath pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you, as a King who confideth in you, who now is commending his perſon into your hands, and commits the verie care of his life to your protection, next to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Studie then to gratifie ſuch preſſing endearments, and provoke not the wrath of Heaven upon your heads by new rebellions. Thoſe who have examined your by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt actions, approve not (doubtleſs) that reſolution that I have taken to return into <hi>France</hi> as I have done; for (they will tell me) what confidence can you have in thoſe who had no regard to their lawful Sovereign? They pretend much to deſire your preſence, but their fears exceed their deſires: And it is rather to ſecure your perſon, then to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance your Scepter; that though you are this day recalled,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48667:8"/>yet as long as your youth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu'd, they ſufferd you to live in exile, and obeyed <hi>Robert;</hi> but he being dead (at preſent) and they ſeeing that you were in a condition to obtain by force that which they now offer, they ſeem to repent, not ſo much regarding your loſſe, as themſelves. Behold the reaſons which have here conteſted with my reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which (ſeeing they are not without ſome rationall ground) I have not deſiſted to perſwade my ſelf, and that in double choice, whether to make a War with you, or confide in you, I have choſe the latter as more glorious, and <hi>I love rather to hazard my perſon then the deſtruction of all my Kingdoms.</hi> Thoſe who taught me the art to Reign have well fore-ſeen the Exigencies to which I am now reduced, and therefore without doubt they took ſo much care to adviſe me what to do in juſtice, and what I might be allowed to do in Clemencie: Theſe two Virtues ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as contraries, but are not; they accord eaſily in the heart of a Prince. They mutually give place each one to the other in the Empire of his Soul, according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers occaſions which are preſented, for he ought alwaies to abound in Clemencie, and he ought not likewiſe to be ever too ſevere with the ſtrict meaſure of juſtice. <hi>Mercie and juſtice are two excellent Virtues, but Prudence ought to imploy them both: And the Princes ſole Will, ought to be the only rule to guide them.</hi> Having then conjured you to an equall confidence in me, as I have in you, let an Act of Oblivion paſs, and <hi>let us remember no more former crimes, unleſſe it be to prevent relapſes.</hi> Let us not look on the Tombe of <hi>Charles,</hi> but merely to bedew it with the tears of tender Repentance: Not to make it an Altar where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to ſacrifice his Enemies; let us Raze to the ground thoſe horrid Cells which ſerved for his Impriſonments
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48667:9"/>thereby (if poſſible) to deſtroy the memorie, and not to leave a mark or point to poſterity of thoſe black crimes; let us aſcend the Throne with as much ſplendor as if it had never been prophaned, and let us Reign (if poſſible) with more honor and tranquillity then the late King my Soveraign did. But do not think I ſhall be able to effect it without the aid and ſuccours of my Subjects; deceive not your ſelves, <hi>the valour and prudence of the Prince are not ſufficient of themſelves to make a Kingdom happy:</hi> The Subjects ought to contribute their proportions. The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are to offer their loyall Obedience, and the people to follow their good example, and both degrees ought to be united in virtue: for otherwiſe he who giveth Victory and Maſters Fortune, will approve the virtue of the Prince in puniſhing the vice of the Subjects. <hi>Thoſe who are valiant, do not alwaies gain the Battail; and thoſe who are wiſe, are not alwaies fortunate:</hi> However let us place our ſelves in ſuch a capacity, that we may be ſucceſsfull, though we cannot merit it. See here what your Prince hath ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, who in Lieu of puniſhing you, hath pardoned you; inſtead of fighting with you, prepares to defend you; inſtead of being your Enemy, becomes your Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and who by his own birth and your choice, is now your Lord, your Maſter, and your King. Theſe two qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities permit me not to Capitulate farther with you: It ſufficeth that I onely adde this; That I admit you to hope for clemencie, whileſt I Reigne, as I wiſh you to fear alwayes my juſtice, and beware that you put not your ſelves in a condition to make trial of the ſecond, or of looſing the former.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48667:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
